<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="historicRecipes.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<recipe name = "Lentils of Arabia"> <title>"Lentils of Arabia" with Rice, Cumin, and Carmelized Onions</title>
   
   <about>
      About this Recipe
      Servings: 6 
      Serving Size: 2/3 cup
   </about>
    
<credit>With thanks to Canola Info</credit>
    
<list type= "ingredients">
    <label> Ingredients </label>
<item type="dry" quant=".5" unit="cup" xml:id="frlentil">1/2 cup brown French lentils</item>   
<item type="dry" quant=".5" unit=".5 cup" xml:id="lwhrice">1/2 cup long grain white rice </item>
    <item type="dry" quant="5" unit="cup" xml:id="water">5 cups water 1.25 L</item>
    <item type="spice" quant="2" unit="Tbsp" xml:id="grcoriander">2 Tbsp ground coriander seeds 30 mL</item>
   <item type="spice" quant="1" unit="Tbsp" xml:id="grcumin"> 1 Tbsp ground cumin seeds 15 mL</item>
    <item type="wet" quant=".25" unit="cup" xml:id="canoil">1/4 cup canola oil 60 mL</item>
    <item type="veggies" quant="2" unit="whole" xml:id="yellonion">2 large yellow onions, cut in half lengthwise and thinly sliced</item>
    <item type="spice" quant="1" unit="tsp" xml:id="salt">1 tsp coarse sea or kosher salt 5 mL</item>

</list>
<list type="equip">
<item>Medium Saucepan</item>
<item> Stove </item>
<item> Ladle </item>
<item> Large Skillet or Wok (preferred) </item>

</list>   

<list type= "Instructions">
    <listName>Making and Cooking It</listName>
    <item type= "1">In medium saucepan, add <ingred ptr="#frlentil">lentils</ingred> and fill pan halfway with water. Rinse <ingred ptr="#frlentil">lentils</ingred> by rubbing them between your fingertips. Water will become cloudy; drain it. Repeat three or four times, until water remains relatively clear then drain. </item>
<item type="2">Now add <ingred ptr="#lwhrice">rice</ingred> and 5 cups (1.25 L) water. Bring water to boil over medium-high heat. Skim off and discard any foam that may form on surface. Stir in <ingred ptr="#grcoriander">coriander</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#grcumin">cumin</ingred>. Lower heat to low and simmer, covered, stirring occasionally, until <ingred ptr="#lwhrice">rice</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#frlentil">lentils</ingred> are soft and creamy in texture, similar to cooked risotto, 45 minutes to 1 hour. </item>
<item type="3">While grains cook, in large skillet or wok (preferred), heat <ingred ptr="#canolaO">canola oil</ingred> over medium heat. Once oil appears to shimmer, add <ingred ptr="#yellonion">onion</ingred> and stir-fry until it turns deep caramel brown in color, 25 to 30 minutes. </item>
<item type="4"> Once <ingred ptr="#frlentil">lentils</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#lwhrice">rice</ingred> are cooked and porridge-like in consistency, stir in <ingred ptr="#yellonion">onion</ingred> along with <ingred ptr="#salt">salt</ingred> and serve warm. </item>   
</list>
    
    <note n="1" type="Presentation"> Cook’s Tip: For a more colorful presentation, serve this stew alongside a platter of fresh cut vegetables like cucumbers, tomatoes, raw red onions and wedges of lime. Like it hot? A few sliced chiles are a welcome addition. Or try a simple dollop of spiced, thickened yogurt. Sprinkle in some fresh mint and shred a handful of cucumbers for textural contrast. </note>
    
    
</recipe>
