<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="historicRecipes.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<recipe name = 'Pork Tenderloin with Five Spice Powder and Peppers'>
    <title>Pork Tenderloin with Five Spice Powder and Peppers</title>
<about>
    servings = 4
    serving size = 1 cup
</about>
    <credit>With thanks to canola oil!</credit>
    
    <list type='ingredients'>
        <label>Ingredients</label>
<item type ='wet' quant='2' unit ='tbsp' xml:id='tompaste'>2 Tbsp tomato paste</item>
<item type ='wet' quant ='2' unit='tbsp' xml:id='soySauce'>2 Tbsp soy sauce</item>
<item type ='spice' quant='.5' unit='tsp' xml:id='salt'>1/2 tsp coarse kosher or sea salt</item>
<item type ='spice' quant='2' unit ='tsp' xml:id="fiveSpice">2 tsp Chinese five-spice powder</item>
<item type ='meat' quant='1' unit ='lbs' xml:id='porkTend'>1 lb boneless pork tenderloin, cut into 1/2-inch (1-cm) cubes </item>
<item type = 'dry' quant='2' unit= 'tbsp' xml:id='cornstarch'>2 Tbsp cornstarch</item>
<item type = 'wet' quant='.25' unit='cup' xml:id='canolaO'>1/4 cup canola oil</item>
<item type = 'herb' quant='4' unit='whole' xml:id='garlicClove'>4 large garlic cloves, finely chopped</item>
<item type='herb' quant='2' unit='tbsp' xml:id='freshGinger'>2 Tbsp finely chopped fresh ginger </item>
<item type='veggie' quant='1' unit='whole' xml:id='bellpepp'>1 large red bell pepper, stem and seeds discarded, cut into 1/2-inch (1-cm) cubes</item>
<item type='herb' quant='2' unit='whole' xml:id='cilantro'>2 Tbsp finely chopped fresh cilantro leaves and tender stems </item>
<item type='veggie' quant='3' unit='whole' xml:id="scallion">3 scallions (green tops and white bulbs), sliced into 1-inch (2.5-cm) pieces</item>
    </list>
    <list type = 'Instructions'>
        <label>Instructions</label>
        <item step='1'>In small bowl, stir together <ingred ptr="#tompaste">tomato paste</ingred>, <ingred ptr="#soySauce">soy sauce</ingred>, <ingred ptr="#salt">salt</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#fiveSpice">five-spice powder</ingred>. </item>
<item step='2'>In medium bowl, toss <ingred ptr="#porkTend">pork</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#cornstarch">cornstarch</ingred> together. </item>
        <item step='3'>Heat wok, large skillet or well-seasoned cast-iron skillet over high heat. Drizzle 2 Tbsp (30 mL) <ingred ptr="#canolaO">canola oil</ingred> down sides of wok. When oil forms shimmering pool in bottom of wok, add <ingred ptr="#porkTend">pork</ingred> and stir-fry, stirring constantly, until pork turns slightly brown yet still pink in center, 8 to 10 minutes. </item>
        <item step='4'>Transfer <ingred ptr="#porkTend">pork</ingred> to plate.</item> 
<item step='5'>Trickle remaining 2 Tbsp (30 mL) <ingred ptr="#canolaO">canola oil</ingred> down sides of wok and quickly stir-fry <ingred ptr="#garlicClove">garlic</ingred>, <ingred ptr="#freshGinger">ginger</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#bellpepp">bell pepper</ingred> until some pepper starts to blister, 5 to 8 minutes.</item>
<item step='6'>Add <ingred ptr="#tompaste">tomato paste</ingred> mixture and stir to warm it, about 30 seconds. </item>
        <item step='7'>Return <ingred ptr="#porkTend">pork</ingred> to wok, including any juices from plate, and stir well to combine ingredients and season meat and vegetable with aromatic sauce. Once <ingred ptr="#porkTend">pork</ingred> feels hot to touch, 2 to 4 minutes, stir in <ingred ptr="#cilantro">cilantro</ingred> and <ingred ptr="#scallion">scallions</ingred>, and serve immediately.</item>


    <note n='1'>Cook’s Tips: Most supermarkets and Asian grocery stores carry a five-spice powder blend. If not, make your own by combining:
    . 1 1/2 tsp (7 mL) fennel seeds,
    . 1 1/2 tsp (7 mL) whole cloves,
    . 1 1/2 tsp (7 mL) Sichuan peppercorns (or 2 tsp/10 mL ground),
    . 6 star anise (or 2 tsp/10 mL ground) and
    . 3 3-inch (7.5-cm) long cinnamon sticks, broken into smaller pieces,
    in a spice grinder. Grind until the texture resembles that of finely ground black pepper. Some of China’s signature dishes, such as Peking duck, barbecued spare ribs and roast pork, are flavored with this classic blend. Other five-spice powders may include cardamom, cassia (instead of cinnamon), ginger, nutmeg and even licorice root.
If doubling or tripling this recipe, cook the dish in two or three separate batches to retain that wok-seared, smoky flavor. If you overcrowd the pan, the ingredients will be stewed as opposed to stir-fried and seared, and the consequence will be blah-tasting fare.</note>
    </list>
</recipe>